<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sipxecs SYSTEM "../config/sipxecs_entities.ent">
%sipxecs;
]>
<article lang="en">
  
  <!-- 
       - Copyright (C) 2008 Pingtel Corp., certain elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.  
       - Contributors retain copyright to elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.
       - Licensed to the User under the LGPL license.
  -->

  <title>&sipxecs; SSL Key and Certificate Installation</title>

  <warning>
    <para>
      This Is Not Optional.
      Without SSL, sipX will not merely operate insecurely;
      it will not work at all.
    </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
    sipX relies on SSL to secure communications between some of its
    distributed components, and to protect parts of its web interfaces, so
    your installation requires an SSL key and certificate.  
  </para>
  <para>
    Creating these files need only be done once, regardless of how many sipX
    components you are using.  (The installation instructions for each of the
    components that requires SSL direct you to these instructions.)  You can
    create these files at any time before you attempt to start sipX (or
    test Apache or any other secured component of sipX).
  </para>
  <para>
    There are two ways to create your certificate file; either requires that
    you create a local key for your server and a Certificate Signing Request
    (CSR).  The instructions below will help with these steps.  The two
    sources for a certificate are: 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Obtaining a certificate from a Certificate Authority, or</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>"Self-Certifying" (acting as your own Certificate Authority)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    Your company may have a source for certificates.  (If you have a secured
    web site, you almost certainly do.)  If so, and you are planning to use
    sipX in production, it is best to obtain a certificate from
    your existing Certificate Authority.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you do not have a relationship with a Certificate Authority, you can
    act as your own Certificate Authority.  This provides significant
    security to communications between the sipX components, but it is not as
    secure as using a certificate obtained from a Certificate Authority.
  </para>
  <para>
    This choice is not a permanent one - you can use self-certification as a
    temporary measure and switch to using a certificate from a Certificate
    Authority later.  To change the certificate, you must install new
    certificate and key files into sipX in the same way you installed the
    first set (which is described in some detail below). 
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Obtaining a certificate from a Certificate Authority</title>

    <para>
      This method is a little less quick and convenient for you to set up
      initially, because you must generate a Certificate Request and send it to
      the Certificate Authority to obtain your certificate.  However, it is
      probably more secure and is easier for your users because the browsers
      they use will probably already trust certificates issued this way.
    </para>
    <para>
      Your Certificate Authority may have its own instructions for how to
      generate a Certificate Request.  A sipX system can use a web
      server certificate, so follow the instructions from your CA on how to
      request a certificate to secure an Apache web server. 
    </para>
    <para>
      If your Certificate Authority has not given you instructions on how to
      generate a request, you can create a Certificate Signing Request and key
      by running the gen-ssl-keys.sh script.  (The details are listed below.)  
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Self-Certifying</title>
    <para>
      This method is quicker, but is slightly less secure because your
      certificate signing key is not protected by a Certificate Authority.
      Also, your users will see warning messages when they first access your
      server because the certificate is not derived from a well-known
      authority.  (They can choose to accept your certificate, which will
      eliminate future warnings.)
    </para>
    <para>
      To use this method, run the gen-ssl-keys.sh script and then follow the
      instructions under Key and Certificate Installation below.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Running gen-ssl-keys.sh</title>
      <para>
        gen-ssl-keys.sh is usually installed as /usr/bin/ssl-cert/gen-ssl-keys.sh.
        It may be in a different location if sipXecs is built with a non-standard
        directory prefix.  Adjust the examples below to fit your installation.
      </para>
      <para>
        The gen-ssl-keys.sh script can be run in a few different ways depending
        on how you want to manage your certificates:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To generate a self-signed certificate for a single system:
              <informalexample>
                <screen>
                  /usr/bin/ssl-cert/gen-ssl-keys.sh
                </screen>
              </informalexample>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To generate a private key and certificate request for use
              with a public or private certificate authority:
              <informalexample>
                <screen>
                  /usr/bin/ssl-cert/gen-ssl-keys.sh --csr
                </screen>
              </informalexample>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To generate a private self-signed authority certificate you can use
              to sign certificates for multiple systems:
              <informalexample>
                <screen>
                  /usr/bin/ssl-cert/gen-ssl-keys.sh --new-ca
                </screen>
              </informalexample>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To sign a certificate for your server using your own authority
              certificate (as generated above):
              <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>gen-ssl-keys.sh</command>
                <arg choice='req'>--sign <replaceable>csr-file</replaceable></arg>
                <arg choice='opt'>--ca <replaceable>ca-name</replaceable></arg>
                <arg choice='opt'>--ca-key <replaceable>keyfile</replaceable></arg>
              </cmdsynopsis>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        gen-ssl-keys.sh is "safe"; it does not modify any part of your sipX
        configuration.  The actual installation of the certificates and key it
        generates are described under Key and Certificate Installation below.
      </para>
      <para>
        To use gen-ssl-keys.sh:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Create a temporary directory and change into it.  For example:
              <informalexample>
                <screen>
                  mkdir $HOME/sslkeys
                  cd    $HOME/sslkeys
                </screen>
              </informalexample>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        Run the script:
      </para>
      <para>
        It prompts you for the following information about your organization:
        <informalexample>
          <screen>
            Country Name (2 letter code) [] : 
            State or Province Name (full name) [] :
            Locality Name (eg, city) [] :
            Organization Name (eg, company) [] :
            Organization Unit Name (eg, section) [VoIP Services] :
          </screen>
        </informalexample>
      </para>
      <para>
        Depending on which form you used (see above), it may also request:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>CA Common Name (DNS name for CA)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you are self-certifying, provide the DNS domain name of your
              organization with a unique host name _not_ the same as the name of
              your sipX server.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Server Common Name (DNS name for Server)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Provide the DNS name of the sipX server.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>SIP Domain Name</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Like email, the domain part of your sip addresses may be different
              from the DNS name of the server you use; this is where you specify
              the domain part of the addresses for your server.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Email Contact Address for CA (name@example.org)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you are making a request to a Certificate Authority, provide
              their e-mail contact address.  If you are self-certifying,
              provide the e-mail contact address for someone responsible for
              sipX.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Email Contact Address for Server (name@example.org)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Provide the e-mail contact address for someone responsible for the
              specific sipX server.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id='installation'>
    <title>Key and Certificate Installation</title>

    <section id='installation.wellknown'>
      <title>Well Known Certificate Authority</title>
      <para>
        The gen-ssl-keys script produces:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>The server key (<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>.key)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is your private key - it must be kept secret.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>The server certificate request (<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>.csr)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is sent to the certificate authority to provide them the information to be signed.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        To obtain your key from a Certificate Authority, send the CSR
        file to your CA for signing.  The CA will give you a certificate
        file; copy it to the directory with the <replaceable>hostname</replaceable>.key file;
        name it '<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>.crt', and then as root run:
      </para>
      <informalexample>
        <screen>
          # Must be ROOT
          /usr/bin/ssl-cert/install-cert.sh <replaceable>server-key-file</replaceable>
        </screen>
      </informalexample>
      <para>
        (Similarly to gen-ssl-keys.sh, install-cert.sh is usually installed
        as /usr/bin/ssl-cert/install-cert.sh.)
      </para>
      <para>
        If the installation fails, it may be because you need to install a 
        root certificate from the CA.  If the install script detects that
        this is the problem, it will print the file name you need to copy 
        the root certificate to and rerun the install-cert.sh.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id='installation.selfsigned'>
      <title>Self-signed Certificate Authority</title>
      <para>
        There are some additional files used in this method:
      </para>
      
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>CA key</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The CA key file MUST be kept as secure as you can make it.  It is
              the foundation of all the security provided by SSL.  You do not
              need regular access to this file, so moving it to offline storage
              would be an appropriate precaution.  If you do this, then when you
              sign a new server key, you need to pass the location of this CA
              key using 'gen-ssl-keys.sh --ca-key <replaceable>ca-key-filename</replaceable>'.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>CA and Server certificates</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To install these certificates and the server key on this system,
              run the following command as root in this directory.
            </para>
            <informalexample>
              <screen>
                # Must be ROOT
                /usr/bin/ssl-cert/install-cert.sh
              </screen>
            </informalexample>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>

