<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY sipxecs "sipXecs">
<!ENTITY sipxrelease "4.0">
<!ENTITY sipxecspgk "sipxecs rpm">
<!ENTITY sipxconfig "sipXconfig">
<!ENTITY sipxsuper "sipXsupervisor">
]>
<article lang="en">
  
  <!-- 
    - Copyright (C) 2008 Pingtel Corp., certain elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.  
    - Contributors retain copyright to elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.
    - Licensed to the User under the LGPL license.
  -->

  <title>&sipxecs; Installation, Setup, and Configuration Specification</title>

   <articleinfo>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Describes how a &sipxecs; system is installed, including initial
        configuration, and how service processes are managed.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.4</revnumber>
        <date><?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d X"?></date>
        <revremark>removed some detail that has moved into doxygen documentation</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.3</revnumber>
        <date>2008-06-17</date>
        <revremark>reworked initial setup, simplified process states</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
        <date>2008-05-29</date>
        <revremark>added detail with high level design information</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
        <date>2008-03-27</date>
        <revremark>Functional Requirements Review</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id='scenarios'>
    <title>Scenarios</title>

    <para>
      This section is organized as a series of user workflow narratives:
      steps that a user (usually a &sipxecs; administrator) takes to
      accomplish some end.  
    </para>  

    <section id='inst'>
      <title>Installation</title>

      <section id='inst.single.iso'>
        <title>Installation of a single system using ISO image</title>

        <para>
          Our administrator chooses a system that meets the hardware
          requirements to be the new &sipxecs; server, inserts the
          &sipxecs; installation CD (or perhaps soon, a DVD) in the drive,
          and boots from it.  After a prompt to ensure that it is
          acceptable to re-initialize the system and destroy all data on
          the drives, the installation runs prompting the administrator for:
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>The password for the system root account</para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              The network parameters:
              <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
                <listitem><para>Host Name</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>IP Address</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Netmask</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Default Gateway IP Address</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>Set the system timezone.</para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>Set the system time, and select ntp servers.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>
          When the installation is complete, the installer ejects the
          installation disk and reboots.
        </para>

        <para>
          Following the reboot, the administrator starts a web browser on
          some other system connected to the same network and directs it to
          the new &sipxecs; system.  The new &sipxecs; system is in a
          special setup mode, described in <xref linkend='setup'/>.
        </para>

      </section>

      <section id='inst.single.rpm'>
        <title>Installation of a system using RPMs</title>

        <para>
          Installation from RPMs can be done either by installing the 
          individual rpms manually, or by configuring the package
          manager (yum, apt, or whatever) to include a repository
          containing them and directing the package manager to install the
          required components.
        </para>

        <para>
          The &sipxecspgk; that installs all the &sipxecs;
          components.  The recommended installation method is to install
          this umbrella rpm so that all components are installed.
        </para>

        <para>
          Following installation, the administrator must either reboot the
          system, or manually start the &sipxecs; services, and then
          connect to the web interface for initial setup (see <xref linkend='setup'/>).
        </para>

      </section>

      <section id='setup'>
        <title>Initial Configuration with &sipxconfig;</title>
        <para>
          The first time that the administrator logs in to the &sipxconfig;
          web user interface, a number of configuration choices must be
          made that establish the basic system parameters and configure
          each of the required services.  Until the required services have
          been configured and activated, ordinary use of the &sipxconfig;
          administrative and user interfaces is not allowed.  This mode
          requests the following information from the administrator using a
          series of setup screens:
        </para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>The password for the superadmin &sipxecs; account</para>
          </step>
          
          <step>
            <para>
              The information needed to generate a TLS/SSL certificate:
              <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
                <listitem><para>SIP Domain Name</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Organization Name</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Country Code</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>State or Province</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Locality (city)</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>
              Having gotten the data above, the system can now switch out of
              the setup mode.  The final setup screen displays a link back to
              the normal &sipxconfig; login screen; following this link
              converts the session to one protected by TLS/SSL and prompts
              for the newly established superadmin password.  
            </para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>establish superuser password</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>configure ntp</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>configure dns</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>configure dhcp</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>tbd</emphasis></para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><emphasis>The list above may be incomplete.  In some
        cases, the user may be allowed to explicitly choose not to
        configure some of the system services.</emphasis></para>

      </section>

      <section id='inst.cluster'>
        <title>Installation of a system cluster</title>
        <para>
          The installation of a &sipxecs; cluster begins with the
          installation of the master system: from an iso image (<xref
          linkend='inst.single.iso'/>) or rpms (<xref
          linkend='inst.single.rpm'/>).  Once the <link
          linkend='setup'>initial configuration with
          &sipxconfig;</link> is complete, the user can choose to <link linkend='dist.add'>add a
          distributed system to the cluster</link> (a single-system installation
          is just a degenerate case - a cluster with only one system).
        </para>

        <section id='dist.add'>
          <title>Adding a distributed system</title>
          <para>
            The configuration operation in &sipxconfig; for adding a new
            system to the cluster requires:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>The fully qualified domain name of the new system.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>The IP address of the new system.</para></listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The set of services to be run on the new system.  Some
                  services (such as &sipxsuper; and ntpd) are required on every
                  system in a cluster.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Additional information may be required depending on what
                  services are selected.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>

          <para>
            The &sipxconfig; generates the initial configuration for the new
            system, including: 
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>A TLS/SSL certificate</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>The configuration files for the services on the system.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            When all required information has been provided and this
            configuration is ready, &sipxconfig; presents an option to
            'Push Configuration'.  This is used after installing the
            software on the system, as described in <xref linkend='inst.dist'/>.
          </para>

        </section>

        <section id='inst.dist'>
          <title>Installation of a distributed system</title>

          <para>
            Once the &sipxconfig; has <link linkend='dist.add'>prepared a
            configuration for the new distributed system</link>, the
            administrator installs the &sipxecs; software on the new system
            either <link linkend='inst.single.iso'>from an iso image</link>
            or <link linkend='inst.single.rpm'>on an existing system from
            rpms</link>.  The administrator then navigates to the screen
            for the new system in &sipxconfig; on the master system, and
            selects the 'Push Configuration' function.  This transmits the 
            prepared configuration from the master system to the
            distributed system.
          </para>

          <para>
            The Distributed System Setup Interface is available only in a newly
            installed system that has not yet been configured.  It allows
            &sipxconfig; to push an initial system configuration to a new
            distributed system.  The interface is a simple HTTP
            PUT operation for a URL on the distributed system.  It is not
            authenticated, since no certificate is available yet.
            <note>
              <para>The construction of the full URL for this request is
              TBD</para>
            </note>
          </para>

          <para>
            The entity accepted by this PUT request is a gzipped tar file
            containing system configuration files to be installed as root from
            the root of the file system.  
          </para>

        </section>

        <section id='service.add'>
          <title>Add a Service</title>
          <para>
            To add a service to an existing installation, the administrator
            uses &sipxconfig; to first select the system in the cluster
            where the service should be added, and configures the service
            to run on that system.  &sipxconfig; then collects any
            configuration information needed to initialize that service,
            and then activates the service.
          </para>
        </section>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id='backup'>
      <title>Configuration Backup and Restore</title>
      <para>
        It should be possible to back up only the master system to fully
        preserve all of the configuration for a cluster.  Following a
        restore operation, &sipxconfig; must regenerate all service
        configurations for all services in the cluster.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id='upgrade'>
      <title>Software Upgrade</title>
      <para>
        The procedure to upgrade a &sipxecs; cluster is as follows:
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            The master system is upgraded first by installing the rpms and
            then restarting the &sipxecs; service.  
          </para> 
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            When the &sipxsuper; starts, it compares its own version
            identifier to that of the current configuration on that system (see <xref
            linkend='config.stamp'/>).  
          </para>
          <substeps>
            <step>
              <para>
                If the previous version identifier is not the same as its
                own version (including if no previous version is recorded),
                &sipxsuper; does not start any configured services except
                &sipxconfig; on a master system. 
              </para>
            </step>
            <step id='config.stamp'>
              <para>
                When &sipxconfig; has confirmed that the stored
                configuration on a system in the cluster is appropriate for
                the version of software installed on that system, it
                invokes an XML RPC interface of &sipxsuper; to update the
                stored configuration version number on that system.  
              </para>
            </step>

          </substeps>
        </step>
        

      </procedure>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id='components'>
    <title>Components</title>

    <para>
      This section is a functional description of the &sipxecs; components
      important to system and service configuration and managment.
    </para>

    <section id='supervisor'>
      <title>&sipxsuper;</title>
      <para>
        The &sipxsuper; is the master process management service for all
        &sipxecs; managed services on a system.   
      </para>

      <section id='process.def'>
        <title>Service Definition</title>
        <para>
          Each service installs a definition for itself in the
          /etc/sipxpbx/process.d directory; these definitions, and the
          commands from &sipxconfig; control the actions of &sipxsuper;.
        </para>
        <para>
          The definition is an xml file using the sipXecs-process-01-00
          schema.  The service definition specifies the name and version of
          the service and has the following major sections:
        </para>

        <section id='process.def.cmd'>
          <title>Service Commands</title>
          <para>
            The command section specifies a command to execute for the
            following standard operations (some are optional): 
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>Test the service configuration.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Start the service.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Stop the service.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Reload the service configuration.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </section>

        <section id='process.def.status'>
          <title>Service Status</title>
          <para>
            The status section specifies the following ways for the
            &sipxsuper; to see the status of the process: 
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>The path to the process id file.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>A path to each log file.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </section>

        <section id='process.def.resource'>
          <title>Service Resources</title>
          <para>
            The resources section specifies each of the resources used by
            the process, and for each whether or not the resource must
            exist before the process can be started.  The resources can be:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>A path to a configuration file.</para></listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The name of another &sipxecs; service that must be
                  running before this service is started.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The name of an in-memory database table that must be
                  loaded before this service is started. 
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The name of a postgres database that must exist before
                  this service is started.  
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>

          <para>
            The &sipxsuper; provides a set of XML RPC operations that allow
            &sipxconfig; to read, create, or modify the non-process resources required
            by any defined service; process resources can only be created
            by installing them and then &sipxconfig; can enable them.  
            
            <note>
              <title>Resource Security</title>
              <para>
                The &sipxsuper; must not provide any operation that will
                create or modify anything on the system that is not
                declared as a resource by some service definition, and must
                not modify any part of any service definition.  This is
                the basis of the system integrity protection.
              </para>
            </note>
          </para>

        </section>
      </section>

      <section id='replication'>
        <title>Configuration Replication</title>
        <para>
          All configuration for each &sipxecs; service is created by
          &sipxconfig; and replicated to the system where the service runs
          through &sipxsuper;.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id='super.start'>
        <title>&sipxsuper; Startup</title>

        <procedure>

          <step>
            <para>
              Before attempting to start any service, &sipxsuper; checks
              whether it is running on the master system:
            </para>
            <substeps>
              <step>
                <para>
                  If it is running on the master system, it proceeds with
                  starting the services on the system (see subsequent steps).
                </para>
              </step>
              <step>
                <para>
                  If it is running on a distributed system, it first
                  invokes a Distributed System Checkin method provided by
                  &sipxconfig; on the master system; the service does not provide
                  any information to the distributed system, and cannot
                  fail, so the &sipxsuper; proceeds as follows regardless
                  of the result.  The purpose of this checkin is to notify
                  &sipxconfig; that the &sipxsuper; service on the
                  distributed system is up so that it can check the
                  distributed system configuration.
                </para>
              </step>
            </substeps>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>
              For each enabled service on the system, &sipxsuper;:
            </para>
            <substeps>
              <step id='super.versioncheck'>
                <para>
                  Compares the version of the process as specified by the
                  process definition against the version written by
                  &sipxconfig; when it configured the service  If the versions match
                  exactly, then &sipxsuper; proceeds to the next step; if not,
                  the state of the service is set to
                  ConfigurationVersionMismatch and no further attempt is made
                  to start the process until this condition has been corrected
                  by &sipxconfig;.
                </para>
              </step>
              <step>
                <para>
                  Checks that each required resource is satisfied.
                </para>
              </step>
              <step>
                <para>
                  If one is defined, it executes the configuration test
                  command defined by the service.  It reads any standard
                  error output and saves it.  The exit status of the test
                  command is checked: 
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        If the status is negative, the service cannot be
                        started.  
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        If the status is greater than zero, the service can
                        be started but the process status is marked as having had a
                        configuration warning.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        If the status is zero, the test passes and the service can be started.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </step>
              <step>
                <para>
                  If all of the tests above pass, the start command for the
                  service is executed.
                </para>
              </step>
            </substeps>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>
          A set of XML RPC operations is provided by &sipxsuper; to
          provide the current status of each enabled service. 
        </para>

     </section>

     <section id='process.mgmt'>
        <title>Service Control and Status</title>

        <para>
          The &sipxsuper; maintains three peices of state with
          respect to each &sipxecs; service for which it has a definition:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The desired state of the service on the system:
              <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>enabled</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>the service process should be active on this system</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>disabled</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>the service should not be active on this system</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist>
              See the documentation of the sipXconfig Process class for an
              illustration of process states.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              The configuration version stamp.
            </para>
            <para>
              This value is set by &sipxconfig; when all configuration for
              the process has been replicated to the system.  It records
              the version of the process for which the replicated
              configuration is intended.  This value is used to check that
              the configuration version matches that of the service process
              before that process is started (see <xref linkend='super.versioncheck'/>).
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              The actual state of the process on the system:
              <variablelist>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>ConfigurationVersionMismatch</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the stored configuration version does not match the
                      version in the process definition (see <xref linkend='super.versioncheck'/>).
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>ResourceRequired</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>some resource required by the process is not available</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>ConfigurationTestFailed</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the service returned a failure status when its
                      configuration test was exectuted.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Starting</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the start command has been issued, the process is
                      not yet known to be running (normally an ephemeral
                      state). 
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Running</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the process is running.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Restarting</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the restart command has been issued, the process is
                      not yet known to be running (normally an ephemeral
                      state). 
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Stopping</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the stop command has been issued, the process is
                      still running (normally an ephemeral state). 
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>NotRunning</term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      the process is not running.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

              </variablelist>

              Additional may be defined in the implementation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>
            <emphasis>
              Whether or not a service should be started is not a part
              of the <link linkend='process.def'>process
              definition</link>: it is separate state controlled by
              &sipxconfig;.  The process definition is read-only data
              about the process installed with the the binaries and other
              static data it needs.
            </emphasis>
          </para>
        </note> 


      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

</article>
