<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY sipxecs "sipXecs">
<!ENTITY sipxrelease "4.0">
<!ENTITY sipxconfig "sipXconfig">
<!ENTITY sipx "sipX">
]>
<article lang="en">
  
  <!-- 
    - Copyright (C) 2008 Pingtel Corp., certain elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.  
    - Contributors retain copyright to elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.
    - Licensed to the User under the LGPL license.
  -->

  <title>
    &sipxecs; Hotelling Feature Specification
  </title>

  <section id='overview'>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      The <firstterm>Hotelling</firstterm> feature provides for defining a
      set of 'hotel' phones whose features and lines are temporarily
      reconfigured for a user when that user 'signs in' to the phone.  The
      reconfiguration is reversed either when the user explicitly 'signs
      out' or after some system-configured elapsed time.
    </para>

    <para>
      The motivation for this feature is to support environments in which
      some users are mobile, so a larger population of users can be
      supported using a smaller number of phones, while preserving the
      personalization of phone settings and capabilities specific for each
      user.
    </para>

    <section id='scenario'>
      <title>Typical User Scenario</title>

      <para>
        The following scenario illustrates how the hotelling feature is
        used.  This section is intended only as an example; it is not
        intended to show all aspects of the Hotelling feature set.
        Subsequent sections more fully define the requirements.
      </para>

      <para>
        Our example scenario takes place in an office of JumboExample Corp
        (a member of the Example family of companies).  JumboExample has
        many field operatives that spend most of thier time away from the
        office, but each has an occasional need to come in to file reports,
        attend staff meetings, and be briefed on changes in JumboExample
        policies.  Joe Schmoe is one of these field operatives.
      </para>

      <para>
        Joe arrives at the office on Monday morning, and goes to the Field
        Operative section, where there are 15 cubicles available for
        operatives when they are in the facility.  Each cubicle is supplied
        with furniture, basic office supplies, a laptop docking station
        with large screen monitor, and a SIP phone.
      </para>

      <para>
        Joe goes down the line of cubicles, past a few that are occupied by
        other field operatives, until he finds one that appears to be
        available.  Before sitting down, he checks the display on the SIP
        phone and sees that the phone display indeed indicates that no one
        is presently logged in to this phone (see <xref
        linkend='unassigned'/>).
      </para>

      <para>
        Joe sits down, puts his laptop in the docking station and the
        picture of his dog on the desk, and then logs in to the phone.  The
        phone in this cubicle is equipped with several speed dial buttons,
        one of which is labeled "Login".  He presses this button and after
        one ring the call is answered by the login autoattendant.  The
        autoattendant prompts him for his personal extension number, which
        he enters, and it then prompts him for his PIN (this is the same
        PIN he uses for voicemail), which he also enters.  After a brief
        pause, the autoattendant confirms that his login is successful and
        instructs him to hang up the phone and wait for it to be
        reconfigured.  Joe hangs up and goes to get coffee (and to see if
        anyone has left unwanted sweets at the coffee station).
      </para>

      <para>
        A moment after Joe leaves the cubicle, the phone reboots (see <xref
        linkend='reconfigure'/>).  When he returns, the first line on the
        phone is displaying that it is now his extension number, and the
        message waiting dispay indicates that he has 2 new voicemail
        messages.
      </para>

      <para>
        Joe presses the 'Messages' key on the phone to connect to his
        mailbox, enters his PIN, and deals with the messages.  Then he uses
        the first speed dial key, which is now programmed to the number for
        the administrative assistant for his team.  The assistant answers
        and preempts his question about where the staff meeting is to be
        held today: she knew from her caller-id display that it was Joe,
        and he always calls to ask.  Other speed dial keys on the phone are
        programmed for his home number and that of his supervisor.
      </para>

      <para>
        While he is reading his email, his supervisor calls: to call him,
        she had just dialled his extension number, not needing to know
        which cubicle he had selected.  She wants him to meet with her at
        the end of the day to go over sales projections in his area for the
        coming month.
      </para>

      <para>
        Before leaving at the end of the day, Joe repacks his laptop and
        photo, and presses the speed dial key that is programmed to log him
        out.  The system answers the call and plays an acknowlegement
        message, but Joe is already on his way home.  After a moment, the
        call disconnects and the phone reboots.  When it comes back up, it
        is again displaying that it is an unassigned phone.
      </para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id='requirements'>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      The following sections describe the functional requirements
      for the Hotelling feature.
    </para>

    <section id='unassigned'>
      <title>Unassigned Hotel Phones</title>
    </section>

    <section id='login'>
      <title>Login</title>

    </section>

    <section id='features'>
      <title>User &amp; Phone Features</title>

    </section>

    <section id='reconfigure'>
      <title>Reconfiguration Process</title>

    </section>

    <section id='logout'>
      <title>Logout</title>

    </section>

    <section id='expiration'>
      <title>Expiration</title>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id='design'>
    <title>Design Overview</title>

    <para>TBD</para>

  </section>

  <!--
      -*- mode: nXML; auto-fill -*-
  -->
</article>
