<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY sipxecs "sipXecs">
<!ENTITY sipxrelease "4.0">
<!ENTITY sipxconfig "sipXconfig">
<!ENTITY sipx "sipX">
]>
<article lang="en" status="draft">
  
  <!-- 
    - Copyright (C) 2008 Pingtel Corp., certain elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.  
    - Contributors retain copyright to elements licensed under a Contributor Agreement.
    - Licensed to the User under the LGPL license.
  -->

  <title>
    &sipxecs; Hotelling Feature Specification
  </title>
  
  <articleinfo>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Describes the Hotelling Feature proposed for inclusion in &sipxecs; version &sipxrelease;. 
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
        <date><?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d X"?></date>
        <revremark>For Customer Review</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
        <date>2008-05-21</date>
        <revremark>For Engineering Review</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>


  <section id='overview'>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      The <firstterm>Hotelling</firstterm> feature provides for defining a
      set of 'hotel' phones whose features and lines are temporarily
      reconfigured for a user when that user <firstterm>checks in</firstterm> to the phone.  The
      reconfiguration is reversed either when the user explicitly <firstterm>signs
      out</firstterm> or after some system-configured elapsed time.
    </para>

    <para>
      The motivation for this feature is to support environments in which
      some users are mobile, so a larger population of users can be
      supported using a smaller number of phones, while preserving the
      personalization of phone settings and capabilities specific for each
      user.
    </para>

    <section id='scenario'>
      <title>Typical User Scenario</title>

      <para>
        The following scenario illustrates how the hotelling feature is
        used.  This section is intended only as an example; it is not
        intended to show all aspects of the Hotelling feature set.
        Subsequent sections more fully define the requirements.
      </para>

      <para>
        Our example scenario takes place in an office of JumboExample Corp
        (a member of the Example family of companies).  JumboExample has
        many field operatives that spend most of thier time away from the
        office, but each has an occasional need to come in to file reports,
        attend staff meetings, and be briefed on changes in JumboExample
        policies.  Joe Schmoe is one of these field operatives.
      </para>

      <blockquote>
        <para>
          Joe arrives at the office on Monday morning, and goes to the Field
          Operative section, where there are 15 cubicles available for
          operatives when they are in the facility.  Each cubicle is supplied
          with furniture, basic office supplies, a laptop docking station
          with large screen monitor, and a SIP phone.
        </para>

        <para>
          Joe goes down the line of cubicles, past a few that are occupied by
          other field operatives, until he finds one that appears to be
          available.  Before sitting down, he checks the display on the SIP
          phone and sees that the phone display indeed indicates that no one
          is presently checked in to this phone (see <xref
          linkend='unassigned'/>).
        </para>

        <para>
          Joe sits down, puts his laptop in the docking station and the
          picture of his dog on the desk, and then checks in to the phone.
          The phone in this cubicle is equipped with several speed dial
          buttons, one of which is labeled "Checkin".  He presses this
          button and after one ring the call is answered by the checkin
          autoattendant.  The autoattendant prompts him for his personal
          extension number, which he enters, and it then prompts him for
          his PIN, he enters the same PIN he uses for voicemail.  After a
          brief pause, the autoattendant confirms that his checkin is
          successful and instructs him to hang up the phone and wait for it
          to be reconfigured.  Joe hangs up and goes to get coffee (and to
          see if anyone has left unwanted sweets at the coffee station).
        </para>

        <para>
          A moment after Joe leaves the cubicle, the phone reboots (see <xref
          linkend='reconfigure'/>).  When he returns, the first line on the
          phone is displaying that it is now his extension number, and the
          message waiting dispay indicates that he has 2 new voicemail
          messages.
        </para>

        <para>
          Joe presses the 'Messages' key on the phone to connect to his
          mailbox, enters his PIN, and deals with the messages.  Then he uses
          the first speed dial key, which is now programmed to the number for
          the administrative assistant for his team.  The assistant answers
          and preempts his question about where the staff meeting is to be
          held today: she knew from her caller-id display that it was Joe,
          and he always calls to ask.  Other speed dial keys on the phone are
          programmed for his home number and that of his supervisor.
        </para>

        <para>
          While he is reading his email, his supervisor calls: to call him,
          she had just dialled his extension number, not needing to know
          which cubicle he had selected.  She wants him to meet with her at
          the end of the day to go over sales projections in his area for the
          coming month.
        </para>

        <para>
          Before leaving at the end of the day, Joe repacks his laptop and
          photo, and presses the speed dial key that is programmed to check him
          out.  The system answers the call and plays an acknowlegement
          message, but Joe is already on his way home.  After a moment, the
          call disconnects and the phone reboots.  When it comes back up, it
          is again displaying that it is an unassigned phone.
        </para>
      </blockquote>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id='requirements'>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      The fundamental goal of the Hotelling feature is to make using a
      <firstterm>Hotel</firstterm> phone as much like using a normally
      assigned phone as possible.  A user that has a normally assigned
      phone should find a Hotel phone as familiar as possible.
    </para>

    <section id='hotel-identity'>
      <title>Hotel Phone Identity</title>
      <para>
        The one difference between a normal user phone and a Hotel phone is
        that a Hotel phone has an identity of its own that is not
        associated with the user.  In some (possibly most) phones, this
        additional identity is visible as an additional 'line' on the
        phone.  When no user is checked in to the phone, this hotel phone
        identity is the only identity associated with the phone (see <xref
        linkend='unassigned'/>).  The hotel phone identity is not an
        extension: it is an internal &sipxecs; identifier, so there is no
        normal way to dial a Hotel phone when there is no user checked in
        to it.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id='unassigned'>
      <title>Unassigned Hotel Phones</title>
      <para>
        A phone that does not have a user checked in has only its hotel
        phone identity.  The display name for the hotel phone identity is a
        fixed string that is identical for any hotel phone; it is
        localizable value meant to convey that the phone does not have a
        user checked in (for example, in English it might be "Open",
        "Unused", or "Available").
      </para>

      <para>
        If the phone has speed dial capability, an unassigned hotel phone
        has a speed dial configured for the 'checkin' service (see <xref
        linkend='checkin'/>).  If the phone supports multiple speed dials,
        then additional speed dial destinations may be configured for a
        hotel phone using the same interface available for configuring
        speed dials for other users; these additional destinations are
        configured <emphasis>after</emphasis> the automatically configured
        checkin speed dial destination.
      </para>

      <para>
        The privileges associated with a hotel phone identity are
        configurable using the same mechanisms that are available to
        configure user privileges.  The default privileges for a Hotel
        phone are very restricted:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            No PSTN calls (other than an emergency number) are allowed.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            No voicemail is allowed (this cannot be changed).
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The autoattendant dial-by-name directory does not include any
            unassigned Hotel phones.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id='checkin'>
      <title>Checkin</title>
      <para>
        A system-defined dial sequence is used to "check in" to a hotel
        phone.  This destination is configured as a speed dial on an
        unassigned phone if the phone supports speed dial (see <xref
        linkend='unassigned'/>.  This dial sequence connects to the
        <firstterm>Hoteldesk</firstterm> service:
      </para>
      <procedure>

        <step>
          <para>
            The hoteldesk service checks to see if the calling identity is
            that of an unassigned Hotel phone.  If not, an audio message is
            played that informs the user that checkin is not available from
            the phone they are using; after the message is complete, the
            hoteldesk service hangs up the call.
          </para>

          <para>
            If the calling phones identity is that of an assigned Hotel
            phone (one that some user is currently checked in to), then an
            audio prompt is played that indicates that the phone is
            currently in use and offers to reconfigure the phone for a new
            user.  If the user responds that reconfiguration is desired, the
            sequence continues as if the phone were unassigned; if not, the
            hoteldesk service hangs up the call.
          </para>

        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            An audio prompt is played instructing the user to enter their
            extension, followed by the pound sign (#).
          </para>

          <para>
            The entered extension is checked to see if it is that of a user
            in the system; if not, a message indicating this is played, and
            this step is repeated.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            An audio prompt is played instructing the user to enter their
            PIN, followed by the pound sign (#).
          </para>

          <para>
            The entered PIN is checked to see if it is that of the selected
            user; if not, a message indicating this is played, and the
            previous step (prompting for the extension) is repeated.
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            If the PIN was correct, an audio message is played indicating
            that the checkin has been accepted, the length of time for
            which it will be in effect (see <xref linkend='expiration'/>),
            and instructing the user to hang up and await reconfiguration
            of the phone.  
          </para>

          <para>
            After the user disconnects the call, the phone is reconfigured
            (see <xref linkend='reconfigure'/>).
          </para>
        </step>
        
      </procedure>
    </section>
        
    <section id='reconfigure'>
      <title>Reconfiguration Process</title>

      <para>
        When a user has successfully checked in (see <xref
        linkend='checkin'/>), the hoteldesk service causes a new
        configuration to be generated for the phone that adds the
        configuration specific to the user.  The phone is then
        told to use this new configuration.
      </para>

      <para>
        See <xref linkend='config-merge'/> for discussion of how the
        user-specific configuration and the phone-specific configuration
        are combined to create the configuration of the checked-in hotel
        phone.
      </para>

      <para>
        Similarly, when the user checks out (see <xref
        linkend='checkout'/>), or the checkin period expires (see <xref
        linkend='expiration'/>), the hoteldesk service causes a new
        configuration to be generated for the phone as an unassigned phone
        (see <xref linkend='unassigned'/>), and the phone is instructed to
        use this new configuration.
      </para>

      <para>
        For all currently supported phones, reconfiguration requires
        that the phone reboot.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id='checkout'>
      <title>Checkout</title>

      <para>
        A system-defined dial sequence is used to "check out" of a hotel
        phone.  This destination is configured as a speed dial if the phone
        supports speed dial and is unassigned (see <xref linkend='unassigned'/>).
        This dial sequence connects to the checkout service:
      </para>
      <procedure>
 
        <step>
          <para>
            The service checks to see if the calling identity is that of an
            assigned Hotel phone.  If not, an audio message is played
            that informs the user that checkout is not available from the
            phone they are using; after the message is complete, the
            hoteldesk service hangs up the call.
          </para>

          <para>
            If the calling phones identity is that of an assigned Hotel
            phone (one that some user is currently checked in to), then an
            audio message is played that indicates that the user is now
            logged out and instructing the user to hang up the phone to
            reconfigure.   
          </para>

        </step>

        <step>
          <para>
            After the user disconnects the call, the phone is reconfigured
            (see <xref linkend='reconfigure'/>).
          </para>
        </step>
        
      </procedure>

    </section>

    <section id='expiration'>
      <title>Expiration</title>

      <para>
        The assignment of a hotel phone to a user is temporary: a system
        configuration parameter determines the maximum duration of a hotel
        phone assignment.  If a user has not checked out from a hotel phone
        when that time has past, a new configuration as an unassigned hotel
        phone is generated for the phone, and the phone is reconfigured to
        that unassigned status. 
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id='principles'>
      <title>Feature Tradeoffs and Restrictions</title>
      <para>
        Some aspects of the user experience in a &sipxecs; system are
        implemented entirely in one or more &sipxecs; service processes,
        others (such as speed dial buttons) are implemented entirely within
        the phone, and many are some hybrid - dependant on both the phone
        and the service configuration.  
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Features that cannot be supported without making changes to
            &sipxecs; service configurations are <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>

    <section id='config-merge'>
      <title>Merging User and Phone Configuration</title>
      <para>
        Phones differ in capability: they may differ, for example, in the
        number of lines they support, the number of speed dials they
        support, whether or not they display busy status for lines, and so
        on.  Since some features configured for a user require that specific
        capabilities be available on the phone, it may be that the
        configuration for a particular user may not be fully realized on a
        particular hotel phone.   For example, if a user has a large model
        phone at her 'normal' desk phone, and has configured many speed
        dial keys, a hotel phone with fewer keys will not be able to
        display all of those entries.
      </para>

      <section id='key-assign'>
        <title>Line and Speed Dial Key Assignments</title>
        <para>
          Line keys on an assigned hotel phone are allocated in this 
          order:

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The identity that the user used to log in to the hotel phone
                (if the user has a non-hotel phone, this is the line that
                would normally be the first line on that phone).
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If the particular phone requires that a line key be used to
                configure an additional identity on the phone (most do),
                then the last key available as a line key is assigned to
                the hotel phone identity.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Any remaining keys that are available as speed dial entries
                are used in the order configured for the user.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            
          </orderedlist>
          <note>
            <para>
              Additional line keys that are configured on other non-hotel
              phones assigned to the user are <emphasis>not</emphasis>
              configured on a hotel phone when the user checks in to it;
              such lines are configured only for a specific phone, not for
              the user.
            </para>
          </note>
        </para>
      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id='design'>
    <title>Design Overview</title>

    <para><emphasis>This section will be added when the functionality has been reviewed and agreed to.</emphasis></para>

  </section>

  <!--
      -*- mode: nXML; auto-fill -*-
  -->
</article>
