<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ""
      "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<?rfc private="SIPfoundry sipXproxy" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!--<?rfc strict="yes" ?>-->

<rfc category="std" ipr="none" docName="call-state-events">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Call State Events">sipXproxy Call State Events Specification</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Lawrence" fullname="Scott Lawrence">
    <organization>Pingtel Corp.</organization>
    <address>
      <email>slawrence@pingtel.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>
    <date day="13" month="May" year="2005"/>
    <area>sipXproxy</area>
    <abstract>
    <t>
    Specifies the Call State Events detected by the sipXproxy;
    these can be used to construct Call Detail Records (CDRs) or other
    indications or records of call state.
    </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Overview">
    <t>
    PBX users often require the collection of call information in
    order to validate
    external billing or create internal charge-back systems.  Due to
    the nature of SIP signalling and the disaggregated sipXpbx design,
    a complete record of a call can only be created by observing
    events that occur at different times and in different sipXpbx
    components.  This document specifies the events recorded and which component is responsible for producing a record
    of each.
    </t>

    <t>
    The record of each observed event is called a Call State Event.  <xref target="CSE_DESCR"/>
    describes each of the events to be recorded, the component
    responsible for it (called the "Observer"), the SIP request or
    response from which its information is derived, and the
    information it contains.
    </t>

    <t>
    The UTC time of events as recorded by each Observer is used to
    order the events, which is in some cases important to determining
    the semantics of the event.  As a result, it is important that all
    Observer clocks are as closely syncronized with each other as
    possible.
    </t>

    <t>
      The process of combining the information in a set of Call State Events
      to determine what happened with the call as whole is called Call
      Resolution; this step uses the events as input and produces a more
      traditional Call Detail Record - a single record per call.  This
      process is described in <xref target="RESOLUTION"/>.
    </t>

    <t>
    Call State Events are encoded as XML according to the the schema
    in <xref target="CSE_SCHEMA"/>.
    </t>

      <section title="Common Elements">

      <t>
        All Call State Events have some elements in common; in fact, most
        of each event consists of the common elements.  These common
        elements are:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="&lt;observer&gt;">
          The DNS name of the system that observed the event.
          </t>

          <t hangText="&lt;obs_seq&gt;">
          The sequence number of this event at the observer.  This is used
          by a collector to detect that events from an observer are missing;
          in a complete record, there are no gaps in the sequence numbers.
          </t>

          <t hangText="&lt;obs_time&gt;">
          The (UTC) time at the observer when this event occured; this
          should be expressed to the millisecond, or as near to that
          as the Observer can measure.
          </t>

          <t hangText="&lt;call&gt;">
          The call element is a compound element that describes the
          call itself.  Its dialog component contains the key values
          used to determine which events are in the same call, and the
          full To and From header field values for display purposes.

          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="&lt;dialog&gt;">
            This value is used to correlate the separate events (which may
            even come from different observers) for the same call.  A dialog
            value has three components:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="&lt;call_id&gt;">
              The value from the SIP Call-Id header.
              </t>

              <t hangText="&lt;from_tag&gt;">
              The value from the tag attribute of the SIP From
              header.  In dialogs begun by a UA that only comforms to
              RFC 2543 this will be absent, so it may not appear in all
              events.
              </t>

              <t hangText="&lt;to_tag&gt;">
              The value from the tag attribute of the SIP To header.  This
              element of a dialog is optional, and will not appear in all
              events.
              </t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="&lt;from&gt;">
            The full From header field value.
            </t>

            <t hangText="&lt;to&gt;">
            The full From header field value.
            </t>

            <t hangText="&lt;via&gt;">
            A Via header value from the event; this element may appear
            more than once - the order is significant.  The Via
            elements in a CSE are ordered such that the first element
            is the Via value added by the message originator.
            </t>

          </list>
          </t>

        </list>
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="OBS_MSG" title="Observer Message">
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="XML element name">
        obs_msg
        </t>

        <t hangText="Triggered by">
        Any change in Observer status.
        </t>

        <t hangText="Description">
        Carries a status code for the new status and an optional
        arbitrary text message for display purposes.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
      The Observer State Event is defined to signal changes in the
      Observer that may be useful to the interpretation of the Call
      State Events.  At this writing, only one event is defined: the
      Restart (obs_status = 0) event is sent when the Observer starts
      up.  It is always sent with observer sequence number 0 (zero).
      </t>

      <t>
        An Observer Message may contain an  is the schema URI that the observer is using in generating
        events.  Observers will typically log call events individually, without the
        call_event_sequence container (which would be the natural place for this
        URI).  This allows a post-processor to correctly construct an XML document
        without having the observer having to put the namespace on every element.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="CSE_DESCR" title="Call State Events">

      <section title="Call Request">
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="XML element name">
        call_request
        </t>

        <t hangText="Triggered by">
        A Call Request Event is generated by the sipXproxy server when an INVITE
        request is received that does not have a tag parameter on the To
        field value.
        </t>

        <t hangText="Description">
        Represents an attempt to create a new call.  The
        &lt;contact&gt; element in this event is the calling party
        Contact header field value.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
      Note that in the case of a spiral, where aliases and/or
      redirections cause new INVITE messages to be created, the same
      call generates multiple Call Request events.  Since it is
      possible for these
      different events to be recorded by different observers, the
      observer timestamp (not the observer sequence number) is used to
      determine the original event.
      </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Call Setup">
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="XML element name">
        call_setup
        </t>

        <t hangText="Description"> Indicates acceptance of a call, or
        acceptance of a request to reconfigure a call.  The
        &lt;contact&gt; element in this event is the called party
        Contact header field value.
        </t>

        <t hangText="Triggered by">
        Any 2xx response to any INVITE request.
        </t>

      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
      This event is correlated with a Call Request event by comparing
      the call_id and from_tag values; the to_tag value will not
      appear in the original call_request event, so it is not used.
      </t>
      <t>
      Re-invites will appear as cse_setup events, so putting a call on
      hold or renegotiating the codecs during a call (as, for example,
      when another leg is added to a conference) will generate spurious
      cse_setup events.  These duplicates can be detected by detecting
      duplicate dialog ids and using only the one with the lowest
      observer timestamp (obs_time) value; this is the one that actually
      indicates that the call has been set up.
      </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Call Failure">
      <t>

      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="XML element name">
        cse_failure
        </t>

        <t hangText="Description">
        Indicates that at least one leg of a Call Request
        was rejected.
        </t>

        <t hangText="Triggered by">
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Any 5xx or 6xx response to an INVITE request,</t>
          <t><spanx style="emph">or</spanx> any 4xx response to an
          INVITE request <spanx style="emph">except</spanx>:
          <list>
            <t>401 Authentication Required</t>
            <t>407 Proxy Authentication Required</t>
            <t>408 Request timeout</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Depending on the specific failure mode and the retry
        behaviour of the servers and endpoints, there may be
        more than one Call Failed event for a given attempt to
        create a call; these should all have the same dialog
        ids.  A call state processor can only conclude that all given
        Call Request event ended in failure if there are no Call Setup
        events for it and there are no missing events.
      </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Call End">
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="XML element name">
        cse_end
        </t>

        <t hangText="Description">
        Termination of a successful call.
        </t>

        <t hangText="Triggered by">
        Any BYE request.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
      The Call End event is correlated with a Call Setup event using the
      dialog id.
      </t>
      </section>


    </section>

    <section title='Call State Event Logs'>
      <t>
        In the present implementation, Call Request, Call Setup,
        Call Failure, and Call End events are logged by
        the sipX proxy in the file configured by the directive
        SIPX_PROXY_CALL_STATE_LOG (by default "sipxproxy_callstate.log" in
        the log directory).
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor='RESOLUTION' title="Call Resolution">
      <t>
        The Call State Events described above are not a convenient form for
        applications such as billing or usage monitoring.  For these kinds
        of applications, a more suitable form would be a single record that
        included the parties to the call, when it occurred, and its
        duration.  This form is usually called a Call Detail Record (CDR).
        This section describes the algorithm for constructing CDRs from a
        set of Call State Events.
      </t>

      <t>
        <spanx style="strong">
          At this writing, we do not have an implementation of a resolver;
          if you would like to work on one and contribute it, please
          contact the project coordinator through the tracker or the
          sipx-dev mailing list.
        </spanx>
      </t>

      <t>
        In the following algorithm, the notation:
        <figure>
          <artwork>
/dest-ns:dest-element/dest-sub &lt;- /src-ns:src-element/src-sub
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        is used to indicate that the contents of element path
        /dest-element/dest-sub in the namespace dest-ns should be set from
        the contents of the element /src-element/src-sub from namespace src-ns.
      </t>
      <t>
        The namespaces used are:
        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText='cdr'>
            The Call Detail Records namespace:
            http://www.sipfoundry.org/sipX/schema/xml/cdr-01-00 (see <xref target='CDR_SCHEMA'/>).
          </t>
          <t hangText='cse'>
            The Call State Event namespace: http://www.sipfoundry.org/sipX/schema/xml/cse-01-00 (see <xref target='CSE_SCHEMA'/>).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        To produce the Call Detail Records for a given set of Call State
        Events:
        <list style='numbers'>
          <t>
            Select the events that relate to the same call using the
            information in the &lt;cse:dialog&gt; element.  The &lt;cse:call_id&gt;
            values must match exactly.  If present, the &lt;cse:from&gt; and
            &lt;cse:to&gt; values must not be different, but some events in the
            call may not have one or both of these, and should be considered
            to be a match so long as the &lt;cse:call_id&gt; value matches.
          </t>
          <t>
            Order the events within a call by the value of the
            &lt;obs_time&gt; element.
          </t>
          <t>
            Find the first &lt;cse:call_request&gt; event (if none is
            found, then some data is not available, and the data for this
            call is discarded).
            <figure>
              <artwork>
/cdr:call/caller/uri &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_request/call/from
/cdr:call/called/uri &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_request/call/to
/cdr:call/caller/endpoint &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_request/via
/cdr:call/caller/contact &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_request/contact
/cdr:call/start &lt;- /cse:call_event/obs_time
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            If there is at least one &lt;cse:call_setup&gt; event, find the first
            &lt;cse:call_setup&gt; event
            <figure>
              <artwork>
/cdr:call/called/endpoint &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_setup/via
/cdr:call/called/contact &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_setup/contact
/cdr:call/setup &lt;- /cse:call_event/obs_time
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            Provisionally set
            <figure>
              <artwork>
/cdr:call/completionCode &lt;- CIP
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            Find the last &lt;cse:call_end&gt; event whose
            &lt;cse:dialog&gt; values exactly match those in the selected
            &lt;cse:call_setup&gt;.  If none is found, this is a partial
            record, and it will not have a &lt;cdr:call_end&gt; element.
            If one is found, set:
            <figure>
              <artwork>
/cdr:call/end &lt;- /cse:call_event/obs_time
/cdr:call/completionCode &lt;- CC
              </artwork>
            </figure>
            If there was no &lt;cse:call_setup&gt; event, find the last
            &lt;cse:call_failed&gt; event and set:
            <figure>
              <artwork>
/cdr:call/caller/endpoint &lt;- /cse:call_event/call_failed/via
/cdr:call/end &lt;- /cse:call_event/obs_time
/cdr:call/completionCode &lt;- UC
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>

    <section title="Call State Event XML Schema" anchor="CSE_SCHEMA">
      <figure>
        <artwork>
<?rfc include="call_event_schema.esc"?>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="CSE_EXAMPLES" title="Example Call State Events">
      <figure>
        <artwork>
<?rfc include="call_event_examples.esc"?>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Call Detail Record XML Schema" anchor="CDR_SCHEMA">
      <figure>
        <artwork>
<?rfc include="call_detail_record_schema.esc"?>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>


  </back>

</rfc>
